{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The Soviet-built Salang Tunnel in this mountain range connects Tokharistan [toe-CAR-ee- stan] with points south, shortcutting the Shibar (SHY-bar) Pass. Tirich Mir [TEE-rich meer] is the highest point of this range, which is home to the Kokcha [COKE-cha] Valley’s ancient mines of spinels and lapis lazuli. The massacre of William Elphinstone’s army took place in this range in 1842 as a British force marched to Jalalabad [JUH-la-la-Bad] from Kabul. For 10 points, name this mountain range that runs through Afghanistan and northern Pakistan.",
      "answer": "Hindu Kush Mountains"
    },
    {
      "question": "A painting by Jacques-Louis David shows this man receiving alms while a soldier watches, astonished. Procopius recounts the lurid tale of this man being cuckolded by his adopted son Theodosius. This man's greatest victories include beating the Sassanids at Dara and the Vandals at Tricamarum [try-CAM-er-UM]. This man's first Italian campaign ended after an offer to be made emperor aroused Justinian's suspicions. For 10 points, name this Byzantine general who reconquered Italy and much of North Africa for the empire.",
      "answer": "Belisarius"
    },
    {
      "question": "At a competition in the Soviet Union, American pianist Van Cliburn [CLYE-burn] led an acclaimed performance of this composer's Piano Concerto No. 1 in B-flat minor. This composer supported the eventual victors of the Serbo-Turkish War with his Marche Slave [Marsh slav]. Another of his pieces commemorates the Battle of Borodino by pitting the anthems \"La Marseillaise\" [Mar-SAY-ez] and \"God Save the Tsar\" against each other. For 10 points, name this composer of the 1812 Overture.",
      "answer": "Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky"
    },
    {
      "question": "Jamshid [Jum-SHEED] could perform this action using a cup filled with an elixir of immortality. Methods of doing this in Babylonia made use of texts like Enuma Anu Enlil [Ehn- U-muh AH-nu EN-leel] and entailed the practice of haruspicy [har-OO-spih-see]. This action was performed by priests of Zeus at Dodona [duh-DO-nuh]. This action was performed by augurs in Rome and could involve watching birds or reading the entrails of sheep. For 10 points, name this action that involved determining omens or predicting the future.",
      "answer": "divination"
    },
    {
      "question": "This battle opened with the capture of Fort Douaumont [DOO-uh-mon] and Fort Vaux [Voh]. This battle was conceived as an effort to “bleed” a certain country “white,” and the defenders at this battle were resupplied by a route called “the sacred way.” Erich von Falkenhayn [FALL- kun-hine] was dismissed after losing this battle, which made victorious commander Philippe Petain [Pay-TAHN] a national hero. For 10 points, name this months-long 1916 battle for a town in northeast France.",
      "answer": "Battle of Verdun"
    },
    {
      "question": "The current leader of this political party declared that he had slept with “no more than 30 women” in an interview with GQ. After allegations of a drinking problem, Charles Kennedy stepped down as this party’s leader in 2006. In 2010, this party received 23 percent of the national vote, leading this party to form a governing coalition with David Cameron’s Conservative Party. For 10 points, name this party led by Nick Clegg, a political party in the United Kingdom.",
      "answer": "Liberal Democrats"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to one source, this person died fighting against the Massagetae [MASS-uh-gee- tay], led by Tomyris [Toe-my-ris], who put his head in a jar. This person won the battles of Pteria [tuh-REE-uh] and Thymbra against a rival ruler. This person’s cylinder is considered by some the oldest declaration of human rights. This son of Persis overthrew his grandfather Astyages, rebelling against the Medes [mee-dees]. He was both preceded and succeeded by rulers named Cambyses. For 10 points, name this founder of the Persian Empire.",
      "answer": "Cyrus the Great"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this state, Robert Barnwell Rhett led the Bluffton movement, and the Fort Hill Address was delivered in this state. Events in this state inspired the coining of the phrase \"liberty and union, now and forever\" during the Webster-Hayne debate. The Force Bill allowed the president to send troops to this state. The Tariff of Abominations was attacked in an \"Exposition and Protest\" named for this state. For 10 points, name this state where the Nullification Crisis was sparked by John C. Calhoun.",
      "answer": "South Carolina"
    },
    {
      "question": "The characters in this novel became Japanese schoolgirls in the series Ikki Tousen, or Battle Vixens. A video game series created by Omega Force and Koei that is based on this novel lets you kill opponents to fill your musou bar to perform special attacks, and is called Dynasty Warriors. A two-part John Woo film based on this novel was entitled Red Cliff after a battle in which Cao Cao [Tsao tsao] was defeated. For 10 points, name this basis for a series of twelve tactical RPG games from Koei, a Chinese classic about the battles between the states of Eastern Wu, Cao Wei, and Shu Han.",
      "answer": "Romance of the Three Kingdoms"
    },
    {
      "question": "This theory explains the results of an 1851 experiment by Hippolyte Fizeau [EE-poh-leet FEE-zoh]. This theory can be tested by observing decay rates of muons [MEW-ons]. Lorentz transformations are used in this theory, which gives rise to the ladder and twin “paradoxes” thanks to length contraction and time dilation. This theory posits that the speed of light is the same in all reference frames. For 10 points, identify this theory that Albert Einstein proposed a decade before its “general” counterpart.",
      "answer": "special relativity"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "David Beatty drew one fleet north during this battle, which resulted in a crossing of the T. The flagship of one side of this battle, the Iron Duke, heavily damaged the SMS Konig. During this battle, Admiral John Jellicoe achieved a strategic victory but suffered a tactical loss against the High Seas Fleet under Reinhard Scheer [sheer]. For 10 points, name this battle that took place off of the Denmark coast, the largest naval battle of World War I.",
        "answer": "Battle of Jutland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Following the creation of the HMS Dreadnought, the Royal Navy built what type of large ships such as the HMS Invincible that were much quicker than battleships but vulnerable due to their light armor?",
        "answer": "battle cruisers"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event was the subject of investigations by Admiral Rickover and the Sampson Board. The entity at the center of this event was commanded by Charles Sigsbee, and Joseph Pulitzer edited articles about this event in one of the first examples of Yellow Journalism. For 10 points, name this 1898 event in which a coal explosion may have led to the explosion of a United States sea vessel in Havana Harbor.",
        "answer": "sinking of the USS Maine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other journalist also edited articles of Yellow Journalism. This rival of Joseph Pulitzer published the De Lome Letter.",
        "answer": "William Randolph Hearst"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A canopy designed by this artist is composed of four Solomonic columns adorned with bees, a symbol of the Barberini family. His two sets of “semicircular colonnades lead up to St. Peter’s Basilica, also featuring his Baldacchino [BAL-duh-“key”-no]. Light shines as an angel pierces the title woman with an arrow in his best known work. For 10 points, name this Baroque [buh- ROAK] sculptor of The Ecstasy of St. Theresa.",
        "answer": "Gian Lorenzo Bernini"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This architect of the San Carlo alle Quattro Fontane worked with Pietro da Cortona and under Bernini on the Palazzo Barberini.",
        "answer": "Francesco Borromini"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Persian-dictated “King’s Peace” brought an end to one war named for this city, which the general Lucius Mummius sacked in 146 BC. Ships could be moved across the massive diolkos [dee-OL-kos] ramp constructed by this city’s tyrant Periander. This city named the third primary order of Greek architecture, along with the Doric and Ionic orders. For 10 points, name this Greek city located on a namesake isthmus in the Peloponnesus.",
        "answer": "Corinth"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Like the regions of Thrace and Boeotia [bee-OH-shah], Corinth lends its name to a popular type of what military equipment?",
        "answer": "helmet"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A military junta in this nation fought against the Montoneros and committed the Trelew [truh- LEW] massacre as part of its Process of National Reorganization, actions protested against by the mothers of the Plaza del Mayo. Admiral Jorge Anaya also pushed the junta into a war to redirect internal discontent in this nation. For 10 points, identify this nation where many people disappeared as a result of the Dirty War.",
        "answer": "Argentina"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Argentinian light cruiser named for an independence-era military officer was sunk as one of the early actions of the Falklands War.",
        "answer": "ARA General Belgrano"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The rise of these places is detailed in Kenneth T. Jackson’s Crabgrass Frontier. Victor Gruen attempted to create pedestrian spaces in these areas by designing both outdoor and indoor shopping malls. These places grew in the mid-20th century due to white flight and the GI Bill offering low-interest home loans. For 10 points, name these primarily residential low-density areas that are located outside of major cities.",
        "answer": "suburbs"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the first examples of a prefabricated suburb was this large development on Long Island, which was named after the company that built it.",
        "answer": "Levittown"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Using Brownian motion, the value of a quantity named for this man was determined by Jean Perrin [Puh-RIN]. This man formulated a law stating that the volume of a gas is proportional to the number of particles, which, along with the combined gas law, yields the ideal gas law. For 10 points, name this Italian scientist who lends his name to the number of entities in a mole.",
        "answer": "Amedeo Avogadro"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Avogadro’s number is approximately equal to 6.02 times 10 raised to what integer power?",
        "answer": "the 23rd power"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1900, this state's governor William Goebel [Go-BELL] became the only sitting governor in U.S. history to be assassinated. Andrew Jackson used a campaign song that referred to \"the hunters of\" this state. After initially declaring neutrality in the Civil War, this state eventually stayed with the Union. For 10 points, name this state, the birthplace of Jefferson Davis and Abraham Lincoln.",
        "answer": "Kentucky"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After Kentucky joined the Civil War, this former Southern Democratic presidential candidate from Kentucky resigned from the Senate to become a Confederate general.",
        "answer": "John C. Breckinridge"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "HUNDRED YEARS WAR",
      "prompt": "During the Hundred Years War, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Peasant girl who helped France win the Battle of Orleans?",
          "answer": "Joan of Arc"
        },
        {
          "question": "English king whose claims to the throne of France began the war?",
          "answer": "Edward III"
        },
        {
          "question": "General who captured John II of France at the Battle of Poitiers?",
          "answer": "Edward the Black Prince"
        },
        {
          "question": "Missile weapon whose “long” variety is often miscredited as giving the English a decisive advantage over French knights?",
          "answer": "Bow"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty signed by the Queen of France that made Henry V heir to the throne?",
          "answer": "Treaty of Troyes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Spanish kingdom where the contemporary War of the Two Peters took place, later home to a princess who married Henry VIII?",
          "answer": "Aragon"
        },
        {
          "question": "French port city whose heroic surrendering “Burghers” were sculpted by Auguste Rodin?",
          "answer": "Calais"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the substance the “mad king” of France, Charles VI, believed he was made out of?",
          "answer": "glass"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "WOODROW WILSON",
      "prompt": "Answer some questions about the Presidency of Woodrow Wilson:",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Wilson was the first president from this party since Grover Cleveland.",
          "answer": "Democratic Party"
        },
        {
          "question": "Along with Theodore Roosevelt, Wilson defeated this Republican incumbent in 1912.",
          "answer": "William Howard Taft"
        },
        {
          "question": "This Socialist candidate took 6% of the vote when Wilson was elected.",
          "answer": "Eugene Victor Debs"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wilson signed legislation creating this central banking system.",
          "answer": "Federal Reserve"
        },
        {
          "question": "He restarted the practice of giving this annual message as a speech before Congress.",
          "answer": "State of the Union"
        },
        {
          "question": "Before his political career, Wilson was president of this Ivy League college.",
          "answer": "Princeton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Give the name of Wilson’s progressive agenda.",
          "answer": "The New Freedom"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wilson appointed this advocate of “sociological jurisprudence” known as “the People’s Lawyer” to the Supreme Court.",
          "answer": "Louis Brandeis"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "CIVIL WAR GENERALS",
      "prompt": "Which Civil War General…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Led the Army of Northern Virginia and lost at Gettysburg?",
          "answer": "Robert Edward Lee"
        },
        {
          "question": "As Union general-in-chief received Confederate surrender at Appomattox?",
          "answer": "Ulysses S. Grant"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was killed at Chancellorsville and earned a famous nickname after First Manassas?",
          "answer": "Thomas “Stonewall” Jackson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led the Union to victory in the West with his destructive March to the Sea?",
          "answer": "William Tecumseh Sherman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commanded the Army of the Potomac during the last stages of the war?",
          "answer": "George G. Meade"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was replaced by Hood in the West and led the Confederate retreat after the fall of Atlanta?",
          "answer": "Joseph E. Johnston"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led a Confederate raid on Washington and helped found the Lost Cause interpretation?",
          "answer": "Jubal A. Early"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was nicknamed “Old Brains” and was the Union general-in-chief in the early war?",
          "answer": "Henry W. Halleck"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man used the name of his supervisor, Thomas A. Scott, to issue an order to burn a group of wrecked railroad cars blocking the Pennsylvania Railroad. A company founded by this man built the Eads Bridge in St. Louis. This man, who owned the (20 pts)",
        "Keystone Bridge Company, left Henry Clay Frick with the task of handling the (10 pts)",
        "Homestead Strike. This author of the article \"The Gospel of Wealth\" merged his namesake company with two others to form U.S. Steel. For 10 points, name this Scotland-born steel magnate and philanthropist."
      ],
      "answer": "Andrew Carnegie"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Supporters of this team are known as “Kopites” [CO-pites] and sing along to Gerry and the Pacemakers’ cover of “You’ll Never Walk Alone.” 96 of its fans lost their lives in the Hillsborough Disaster and are the subject of a memorial outside (20 pts)",
        "Anfield. This team contests the Merseyside Derby with Everton and have won the English First Division 18 (10 pts)",
        "times. Last summer, they signed Mario Balotelli to help replace the departing Luis Suarez. For 10 points, name this soccer team managed by Brendan Rodgers and captained by Steven Gerrard."
      ],
      "answer": "Liverpool Football Club"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This scientist postulated that the deficiency in color perception among the color-blind is due to a discoloration of the liquid medium of the eyeball. This man was the first to show that the (20 pts)",
        "pressure of a mixture of gases is equal to the sum of its components’ partial pressures. A mass unit named for this man is equal to (10 pts)",
        "one-twelfth the weight of a neutral atom of carbon, exactly one amu. For 10 points, name this English chemist who developed the law of multiple proportions, a component of his modern atomic theory."
      ],
      "answer": "John Dalton"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The first metal movable type book was printed in this region, which once used a bone rank system. A polity in this region was victorious at the battle of (20 pts)",
        "Salsu River. A kingdom here successfully resisted a Khitan invasion, while a later polity won a decisive victory at Noryang Point through the use of (10 pts)",
        "turtle ships. Sejong the Great is credited with inventing a widely used alphabet in this region, which became a vassal state under Mongol rule before regaining independence under Joseon rule. For 10 points, name this peninsular home of the Goguryeo and Silla dynasties."
      ],
      "answer": "Korea"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Eight members of the Contarini family held this title. People who held this title would board a bucentaur and throw a ring into the sea as part of a symbolic \"marriage\" ceremony. That ceremony celebrates the day a holder of this title conquered Dalmatia, known as (20 pts)",
        "Ascension Day. Ludovico Manin was the last person with this title, whose holders lived in a palace connected to St. (10 pts)",
        "Mark's Basilica and controlled a certain \"Most Serene Republic.\" For 10 points, identify this title held by leaders of a city-state on the Adriatic Sea."
      ],
      "answer": "Doge of Venice"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A future holder of this position declared that “Ginger Rodgers did everything Fred Astaire did, just backwards in high heels” and said that another politician was “born with a silver foot in his mouth” during her keynote speech at the (20 pts)",
        "1988 DNC. Another governor of this state faced controversy over the implementation of the InnerChange Program and the (10 pts)",
        "execution of Karla Faye Tucker. That man defeated Ann Richards for this post and vacated this position after beating Al Gore in the presidential election of 2000. For 10 points, name this position held in the 1990s by George W. Bush."
      ],
      "answer": "Texas Governor"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) William Apess helped organize the successful Mashpee revolt against this state, and settlers from this state launched an expedition against the sachem Sassacus. The Treaty of Casco Bay ended another conflict in this state, in which one side was led by the son of (20 pts)",
        "Massasoit. Edmund Andros served as a governor in this state, which fought the Pequot War and crushed the Wampanoag in (10 pts)",
        "King Philip’s War. Myles Standish committed several massacres as military commander here. For 10 points, name this state in which the Patuxet Squanto saved the colonists arriving in the Mayflower."
      ],
      "answer": "Massachusetts"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man examined the long-term effects of military socialization on soldiers in his recently developed \"social intensity syndrome.\" This man attempted to explain how good people have the capacity to do evil in his book The (20 pts)",
        "Lucifer Effect. A 1971 experiment conducted by this man was funded by the US Office of Naval Research and included the exceptionally brutal (10 pts)",
        "\"John Wayne.\" That experiment placed a divided group of students in a simulated jail for 6 days. For 10 points, name this psychologist who conducted the Stanford Prison Experiment."
      ],
      "answer": "Philip Zimbardo"
    }
  ]
}